Chapter 132. The symphony.
It was a clear steel blue day. The firmaments of air and sea were hardly
separable in that allervading azure.
Only the penceive air was transparently pure and soft with a woman's look. and
the robust and man-like sea heaved with long, strong, lingering swells, as
Samson's chest in his sleep. Hither and thither on high glided the snow white
wings of small unspeckled birds. These were the gentle thoughts of the feminine
air, but to and fro in the deeps, far down in the bottomless blue, rushed
mighty leviathans, swordfish, and sharks. And these were the strong,
troubled, murderous thinkings of the masculine sea.
But though thus contrasting within, the contrast was only in shades and shadows
without those two seemed one. It was only the sex, as it were, that
distinguished them. Aloft, like a royal zar and king, the son seemed giving this
gentle heir to this bold and rolling sea, even as bride to groom. And at the
girdling line of the horizon, a soft and tremulous motion most seen here at the
equator denoted the fond throbbing trust the loving alarms with which the poor
bride gave her bosom away.
Tied up and twisted, gnarled and knotted with wrinkles, haggardedly firm and
unyielding, his eyes glowing like coals that still glow in the ashes of ruin.
Unttotering Ahab stood forth in the clearness of the mourn, lifting his
splintered helmet of a brow to the fair girl's forehead of heaven. Oh immortal
infancy and innocency of the azure, invisible winged creatures that frolic
all around us, sweet childhood of air and sky. How oblivious were ye of old
Ahab's closecoiled woe. But so have I seen little Miriam and Martha, laughing
eyed elves, heedlessly gamble around their old sire, sporting with the circle
of singed locks which grew on the marge of that burntout crater of his brain.
Slowly crossing the deck from the scuttle, Ahab leaned over the side and
watched how his shadow in the water sank and sank to his gaze, the more and the
more that he strove to pierce the profoundity. But the lovely aromomas in
that enchanted air did at last seem to dispel for a moment the cankerous thing
in his soul. That glad happy air, that winsome sky, did at last stroke and
caress him. The stepmother whirled so long cruel, forbidding, now threw
affectionate arms round his stubborn neck, and did seem to joyously sobb over
him, as if over one, that, however willful and airring, she could yet find
it in her heart to save and to bless.
From beneath his slouched hat, Ahab dropped a tear into the sea. Nor did all
the Pacific contain such wealth as that one we drop.
Starbucks saw the old man, saw him, how he heavily leaned over the side, and he
seemed to hear in his own true heart the measurless sobbing that stole out of the
center of the serenity around, careful not to touch him or be noticed by him,
he yet drew near to him, and stood there.
Ahab turned.
Starbucks, sir.
Oh, Starbucks. It is a mild, mild wind and a mild looking sky.
On such a day very much such a sweetness as this, I struck my first whale, a boy
harpooner of 18.
40 40 years ago ago.
40 years of continual wailing. 40 years of privation and peril and storm time.
40 years on the pitilous sea. For 40 years has Ahab forsaken the peaceful
land. For 40 years to make war on the horrors of the deep. I And yes,
Starbucks. Out of those 40 years, I have not spent three aure.
When I think of this life I have led, the desolation of solitude, it has been
the masoned walled town of a captain's exclusiveness, which admits but small
entrance to any sympathy from the green country without oh weariness, heaviness,
guinea coast slavery of solitary command. When I think of all this only
half suspected, not so keenly known to me before, and how for 40 years I have
fed upon dry salted fair, fit emblem of the dry nourishment of my soul, when the
poorest landsman has had fresh fruit to his daily hand, and broken the world's
fresh bread to my moldy crusts.
away whole oceans away from that young girl wife I wetted past 50 and sailed
for Cape Horn the next day leaving but one dent in my marriage pillow wife
rather a widow with her husband alive I I widowed that poor girl when I married
her Starbucks and then the madness the frenzy the boiling blood and the smoking
brow with which for a thousand lowering Old Ahab has furiously foamingly chased
his prey. More a demon than a man. I I
What a 40 years fool. Fool. Old fool has old Ahab been. Why this strife of the
chase? Why weary and Pauly the arm at the ore and the iron and the lance? How
the richer or better is Ahab now?
Behold, oh Starbucks, is it not hard that with this weary load I bear, one poor leg
should have been snatched from under me.
Here, brush this old hair aside. It blinds me that I seem to weep.
Locks so gray did never grow, but from out some ashes.
But do I look very old, so very old?
Starbucks. I feel deadly faint. bowed and humped as though I were Adam
staggering beneath the piled centuries since paradise.
God, God, God, crack my heart, stave my brain. Mockery, mockery, bitter, biting mockery of gray
hairs. Have I lived enough joy to wear ye, and seem and feel thus intolerably old?
Close. Stand close to me, Starbucks. Let me look into a human eye. It is better
than to gaze into sea or sky. Better than to gaze upon God. By the green
land, by the bright Hearthstone, this is the magic glass man. I see my wife and
my child in thine eye.
No. No. Stay on board. On board. Lower.
Not when I do when branded Ahab gives chase to Moby Dick. That hazard shall
not be thine. No, no, not with a far away home. I see in that eye.
Oh, my captain, my captain, noble soul, grand old heart after all. Why should
anyone give chase to that hated fish?
Away with me. Let us fly these deadly waters. Let us home. Wife and child too
are Starbucks. Wife and child of his brotherly sisterly playfellow youth.
Even as thine, sir, are the wife and child of thy loving, longing, paternal
old age. Away. Let us away. This instant let me alter the course. How cheerily,
how hilariously, oh my captain, would we bowl our way to see old Nantucket again.
I think, sir, they have some such mild blue days even as this in Nantucket.
They have. They have. I have seen them.
Some summer days in the morning about this time. Yes, it is his noon nap
now. The boy vivaceiously wakes, sits up in bed, and his mother tells him of me,
of cannibal old me, how I am abroad upon the deep, but will yet come back to
dance him again. It is my Mary, my Mary herself. She promised that my boy every
morning should be carried to the hill to catch the first glimpse of his father's
sail. Yes. Yes, no more. It is done. We head for Nantucket. Come, my captain.
Study out the course and let us away.
See, see the boy's face from the window.
The boy's hand on the hill.
But Ahab's glance was averted. Like a blighted fruit tree, he shook and cast
his last cindered apple to the soil.
What is it? What nameless, inscrable, unearly thing is it? What cousining
hidden lord and master and cruel remorseless emperor commands me that
against all natural lovings and longings I so keep pushing and crowding and
jamming myself on all the time recklessly making me ready to do what in
my own proper natural heart I durst not so much as dare.
Is Ahab Ahab? Is it I, God, or who that lifts this arm?
But if the great sun move not of himself, but is as an errand boy in the
heaven, nor one single star can revolve, but by some invisible power. Then how
can this one small heart beat, this one small brain think thoughts, unless God
does that beating, does that thinking, does that living and not I? By heaven
man we are turned round and round in this world like yonder windless and fate
is the hand spike and all the time low that smiling sky in this unsounded sea.
Look albor who put it into him to chase and fang that flying fish. Where do murderers go,
man? Who's to doom when the judge himself is dragged to the bar?
But it is a mild mild wind and a mildl looking sky. And the air smells now as
if it blew from a far away meadow. They have been making hay somewhere under the
slopes of the Andes Starbucks. And the mowers are sleeping among the new moan
hay. Sleeping. I toil we how we may. We all sleep at last on the field. sleep I
and rust amid greenness as last year's sidesthes flung down and left in the half cut swaths
Starbucks but blanched to a corpse's hue with despair the mate had stolen away
crossed the deck to gaze over on the other side but started at two reflected
fixed eyes in the water there Fedala was motionlessly leaning over the same rail.